Guide to the Monique Wittig Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Monique Wittig papers
1960-2005
GEN MSS 1359
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.58
(30 boxes)
Wittig, Monique, 1935-2003
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, lectures, teaching materials, writings by others, conference materials, printed material, electronic media, and other papers documenting the life and work of Monique Wittig. Writings include manuscripts, typescripts, and corrected proofs for works including Lesbian peoples: Material for a dictionary (Grasset, 1976), Virgile, non (Les éditions de Minuit, 1985), Paris-la-politique et autres histoires (P.O.L., 1999), and The straight mind and other essays (Beacon Press, 1992). Correspondence includes letters from writers, publishers, editors, and others. Teaching materials include syllabi, correspondence, and other papers related to Wittig's teaching at the University at Buffalo and the University of Arizona. Writings by others include writings about Wittig. Also includes correspondence, clippings, writings, and conference materials relating to Nathalie Sarraute.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 23 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Monique Wittig
Monique Wittig (1935-2003) was a French writer and lesbian feminist theorist. She is survived by her partner Sande Zeig, an American filmmaker.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Monique Wittig Literary Estate, LLC. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2014.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: September 2014 Acquisition, Part I; and September 2014 Acquisition, Part II.
The two groupings were acquired at the same time, but were previously received on deposit separately.
Feminism -- France -- 20th Century; Lesbian feminism; Born digital; LGBTQ resource; Sarraute, Nathalie; Wittig, Monique, 1935-2003
- September 2014 Acquisition, Part I, circa 1960s-2000s; 10.0; (23 boxes)
  - Writings, 1960s-2000s
    - Notes on L'Opoponax structure (Box 1)
    - Offprint (tiré à part) French Introduction to Le Corps Lesbien (Box 1)
    - Photocopy of Peter Owen hardcover edition-Les Guerilleres (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Handwritten corrections for Beacon. These are complete corrections as Wittig wanted but these corrections were never made.
    - Les Irreelles (Brouillon pour un dictionnaires des amantes) with handwritten corrections (Box 1)
    - Virgile, incomplete photocopied manuscript with missing pages and handwritten corrections (Box 1)
    - Virgile, Non: galley, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Letter to Guggenheim Fellowship for "The City", undated (Box 1)
    - Virgile, Non: Choice of Name for Manastabal (Box 1)
      One file with handwritten page of names written by Wittig to decide the name of her guide in Virgile, Non.
    - 3 manuscript and typescript early drafts of La Cité (Virgile, non), 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Paris-la-Politique, early working manuscripts, 1980s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Paris-la-Politique, 74 page manuscript with handwritten notes, circa 1985 (Box 3)
    - Paris-la-Politique, later version, circa 1999; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Paris-la–Politique, early version, 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
    - Paris La Pol, proofs, circa 1998-1999; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - The Tchiches and the Tchouches, French and English manuscripts, circa 1983; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Un Jour mon prince viendra, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Le Chantier manuscript (Box 4)
    - Chantier photocopy, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Chantier, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Chantier #2, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - The Straight Mind, 1970s; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Cheval de Troie, circa 1985 (Box 6)
      Typed notes in French and English.
    - Text for Pensee St., original in French, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - The Point of View, undated (Box 6)
    - The Category of Sex, original French and English, 1970s (Box 6)
    - Homo Sum, photocopied manuscript with handwritten corrections, undated (Box 6)
    - L'order du poeme, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Le Brouillon, 1970s-1980s; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Lesbian Peoples, 1980s; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Lesbian Peoples Press, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - The Straight Mind, first layout from Beacon Press (Box 7)
      Numbered on front page 000001 -100.
    - Early manuscript of The Straight Mind (Box 7)
    - The Straight Mind, correspondence and related papers, circa 1991 (Box 7)
    - The Straight Mind: Beacon Galley (Box 8)
    - Lesbian Peoples: Material For a Dictionary manuscript, 3 folders (Box 9)
      Typescript with handwritten page numbers.
    - La mécanique, unpublished manuscript, 1960s (Box 10)
    - Dialogue 2 frères et de la soeur (radio play), 2001 (Box 10)
    - La Recreation, English translation, 1971 January 3 (Box 10)
      Translated into English by Barbara Wright and produced by Martin Esslin.
    - Dialogue in German, October 20, 1970 (Box 10)
    - L'Amant vert, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - L'Amant vert, partial manuscript, undated (Box 11)
    - Le Parloir (5200 Signes), undated (Box 11)
    - Le Grand-Cric-Jules/ Feu de la St-Jean / Le Geographiques, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - La mort du Satyre, short film script, 1970s (Box 11)
    - The Constant Journey, manuscript, in French, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Le Voyage sans fin early manuscript with Avant Note, undated; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - The Constant Journey, in French, 1981; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Le voyage sans fin Paris production items, undated; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Voyage Sans Fin, 8 folders (Box 12)
    - The Constant Journey for Modern Drama, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - The Constant Journey, manuscripts, in English, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - The Constant Journey, US workshops and performances, 5 folders (Box 13)
    - "CD of lecture at poetry center, University of Arizona-Tuscon", 1991-04-27; 1 (Box 23)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - The Girl Story, early manuscript, undated; 6 folders (Box 14)
    - The Girl Story disc, 1 (Box 23)
    - The Girl 1,2,3, undated (Box 14)
    - The Girl Story, undated; 6 folders (Box 14)
    - The Girl Story "coupé", undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - The Girl Story, partial manuscript, undated; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - The Girl Film script, 1990s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - The Girl script, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - The Girl script, corrected, undated; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Notes on The Girl (Box 16)
    - Jeanne d'Arc, in French and English (Box 17)
    - Jeanne d'Arc, full script, in French, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 17)
      One photocopied manuscript of Jeanne d'Arc with original handwritten corrections in red pen.
    - Jeanne d'Arc, script, in English, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 17)
    - Joan of Arc, in English, circa 1980s-2000s; 8 folders (Box 17)
    - Joan of Arc, original English translation, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 17)
      Copy of James Shamus's translation of Jeanne d'Arc with handwritten correction on page 18 in pencil.
    - Jeanne d'Arc, James Shamus letters and contracts, 1988-1989 (Box 17)
    - Jeanne d'Arc manuscript, symbolic exchange in French and English, 1988, 2005; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Jeanne d'Arc typescript, circa 1980s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 17)
      Two typescripts by typist Linda Sullivan of Word Smart with related correspondence and corrections.
    - Jeanne d'Arc, circa 1980s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 18)
      Jeanne d'Arc photocopied script, incomplete original manuscript, and production notes in French and English.
    - Notes on Jeanne D'Arc, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 18)
    - Notes on Jeanne D'Arc (Box 18)
    - Other materials related to Jeanne d'Arc, 1980s-1990s (Box 18)
    - Colloque Nathalie Sarraute papers relating to Sabine Raffy, Lauri Sanou, and Lise Leichbacher, 1990-1991 (Box 19)
    - Colloque Nathalie Sarraute, 1995 October 8 (Box 19)
      Manuscripts of some participants at the UA Colloque on Nathalie Sarraute printed by Lise Leichbacher on 8 October 1995.
    - Galley L'Esprit createur sur Nathalie Sarraute, circa 1995 (Box 19)
      Notes to Lise Leichbacher, original galleys of Nathalie Sarraute, handwritten corrections. Letter from Valerie Minogue with comments on the magazine.
    - Correspondence with editors, 1985-1992 (Box 19)
    - Notes for Lesbian Body lecture at Swarthmore, 1997 March (Box 20)
    - Conference invitations, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 20)
    - Press related materials and academic writings about Wittig, 1980s-2000s (Box 20)
    - Je by Syn Guerin, undated (Box 20)
      French radio play based on The Lesbian Body.
    - No Good Reason, 1981 (Box 20)
      Play by Nathalie Sarraute.
    - Book proposals, 1973, 1975 (Box 20)
    - Proofs, contracts, and notes, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1960s-2000s
    - Letters from writers, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 21)
      Correspondents include Mary McCarthy, Claude Simon, Jean Ricardou, Ludovic Janvier, Claude-Michel Cluny, and Marguerite Duras.
    - Letters from publishers, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 21)
      Correspondents include Jerome and Annette Lindon, Dalmas, Peter Owen LTD, Jean Guichard Meili, Louis Marin, Jean Ruaud, Viking Press, and others.
    - Letters from editors, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 21)
      Correspondents include Who's Who in France, Editions de Minuit, Cercle Francais Du Livre, Svetova Literatura, Giulio Einaudi, David LeVay Margaret Crossland, and others.
    - General correspondence, 1980s-2000s (Box 21)
      Personal and business correspondence including letters about Wittig's green card, and letters from Gerard Genette, Jerom and Irene Lindon, Paul Otchakovsky-Laurens, Joanna Russ, Leo Bersani, Jill Johnston and Ingrid Nyeboe, Martin Duberman, Laura Cottingham, Didier Eribon, Teresa De Lauretis, Germaine Bree, Erika Ostrovsky, PEN American Center, Peter Brook, Margo Viscusi, Lynn Diamond-Nigh, The Center for Lesbian and Gay Studies, George Moskos, and other people or organizations.
    - Various correspondence, 1980s-2000s (Box 22)
      Includes invitations to publish, invitations to conferences and lectures, and a typescript Wittig lecture for David Kessler.
    - Correspondence with related writings, 1980s-2000s (Box 22)
      Includes writings and correspondence about Wittig's bibliography with Namascar Shaktini and Diane Crowder, and an English translation of Paris-la-Politique with Winter Bronwyn and Julia Creet.
    - Other correspondence, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 22)
      Correspondents include Edmond Lutrand, Rowohlt Verlag, David LeVay, Margaret Crossland, Jacques from Yallancou Africa, June Jordan, Aidan Higgens, Mary Daly, Christian Rochefort, and others.
  - Electronic Media
- September 2014 Acquisition, Part II, 1960-2005; 7.58; (7 boxes)
  - Interviews with Monique Wittig, 1996-2001 (Box 24)
    Includes interview materials from Anne Garreta and Dominique Bourque, handwritten notes and corrections, and a phone interview transcript.
  - Reviews of Monique Wittig's works, 1960-2001 (Box 24)
    Includes reviews by Claude Simon, Marguerite Duras, Francois Nourissier, Claude Michel Cluny, Christine Delphy, Jean Duffy, Isabel Contant, Colette Guillauman and others. Published in Observateur, Les Nouvelles Litteraires, Art Press, Le Quotidien de Paris, NQF, Village Voice, Lesbia magazine and others. Reviews of L'OPOPONAX, Dagbladet, Virgile, and others.
  - Correspondence, circa 1970s-2000s
    - Editorial correspondence, circa 1976-1999 (Box 24)
      Correspondents include Jerome Lindon, Ingid Galster, Namascar Shaktin, Marcelle Fonfreide, Claire Devarrieux, and others.
    - Personal and professional correspondence, circa 1975-2000 (Box 24)
      Correspondents include Kate Millett, Germaine Bree, Susan Suleiman, Laura Cottingham, Chaney Holland, Dominique Bourque, Dixie Sheridan, Valerie Minoque, Julia Balen, Michelle Causse, Diane Crowder, Namascar Shaktini, Barie Thorn, Alice Schwarzer, Brad Epps, Suzette Robichon, Susan Wolf, Ericka Ostrovsky, Elizabeth Kennedy, Didier Eribon, and others.
  - Writings
    - By Monique Wittig, circa 1967-1993 (Box 24)
      Includes the Mary McCarthy Conference, l'Order du Poem, Lesbian Body, and others.
    - On Monique Wittig, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 24)
      Includes writings by Kristine Anderson, Julia Balen, Sabine Schrader, Alison Phipps, Diane Crowder, Françiose Armengaud, Namascar Shaktini, and others.
  - Other materials and writings
    - Article on Le Silence de Nathalie Sarraute, 1967 (Box 24)
    - Manuscript of interview with Nathalie Saraute, 1985 (Box 24)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 24)
    - Compagne de Basors Presentation of L'OPOPONAX, 1993 (Box 24)
    - Judith Butler, On The Straight Mind, undated (Box 24)
    - Regents Professorship, 2002 (Box 24)
    - Announcements and flyers for conferences and and The Girl sneak preview, circa 1990s; 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Correspondence relating to a Nathalie Sarraute conference, 1992-1993 (Box 25)
    Includes letters and faxes from Jacques Lasalle, Jean-Yves Tadié, Germaine Brée, Jean-Louis Rivière. Valérie Minogue, Françoise Asso, Françoise Calin, Sally Barbour, Sheila Bell, Roger Shattuck, Anthony Newman, and Arnaud Rykner.
  - Teaching papers, 1990-2005; 8 folders (Box 25)
    Includes syllabi, correspondence, progress reports, and other papers from the University at Buffalo and the University of Arizona.
  - Sketches, contracts, correspondence, press releases, French translation, and other materials relating to The Girl, circa 1990s (Box 25)
  - Pompidou Social Contract, 1999 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, catalog, and press release for Straight Mind, Beacon Press, circa 1992 (Box 25)
    Correspondence, catalog, press release.
  - Lectures and publications related correspondence, 1990s (Box 25)
    Correspondence with Mary Bryson, Georges Moskos and others. Contains invitations,publications and other materials.
  - Papers and related correspondence, circa 1990s; 4 folders (Box 26)
  - Nathalie Sarraute clippings and articles, 1990-1995 (Box 26)
  - LE "for interieur," typescript, 1994 (Box 26)
  - The First International Conference on Nathalie Sarraute, 1994; 3 folders (Box 26)
    Notes, ephemera, correspondence, business paper and other related materials.
  - L'Esprit Creature fax, undated (Box 26)
  - University papers, 1990s-2000s; 15 folders (Box 27)
    Includes notes, student papers, and University of Arizona administrative announcements from the departments of French and Women Studies.
  - University papers, 1990s-2000s; 20 folders (Box 28)
  - Dossier, feminist issues, circa 1980s; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Dossier, Monique Wittig and Colette Monique, circa 1980s (Box 29)
    Correspondence and writings, including Christine Delphy, Simone de Beauvoir, Adrienne Rich, Betsy Warrior, Andrea Dworkin, Monique Graziella and others.
  - Writings and correspondence relating to the Women's Liberation Movement (MLF), France, circa 1970 (Box 29)
  - Articles, posters, and press materials for Psych et Po, 1979
  - Proofs for Le Pensee Straight by Balland with corrections by Monique Wittig, circa 2001; 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Catalogue, ROMANS mode d' emploi, circa 2000s
  - University papers, circa 2000s; 6 folders (Box 30)